Hello, I'm Dr. Yusupov,
and today I will discuss
heart failure from the
clinical perspective.
This lecture is
designed to go hand-in
-hand with cardiomyopathy
pathology lecture
and heart failure
pharmacology lecture.
We will discuss epidemiology
as well as main causes
of heart failure. I
will highlight different
types of heart failure as
well as clinical diagnosis
and principles of treatment.
I will also explain
the importance of
interprofessional collaboration
in heart failure programs
and transitions of care.
The content covered in
this lecture is highly
relevant for the board
study, as you can see here.
I would like to begin
with the case of a 65-year
-old man that you can
read through on your own.
X-ray of the chest is
shown. As we go through the
slides, keep in mind the
history and the presentation,
and we will come back
to this case at the end.
Here's a classic
definition of heart
failure as a clinical syndrome
consisting of cardinal
symptoms, fatigue,
breathlessness,
ankle swelling, that may
be accompanied by signs
such as elevated jugular
venous pressure, pulmonary
crackles, peripheral edema.
It is due to a structural
or functional abnormality
of the heart that results
in elevated intracardiac
pressures or inadequate
cardiac output, whether at
rest or during exercise.
CHF is no longer
a preferred term
because congestion is
not always present.
We still like to use
this terminology, so some
people say C should stand
for chronic heart failure.
Heart failure is a major
public health concern
with substantial
morbidity and mortality.
Statistics given here are
for your reference only.
Prevalence of heart
failure is expected to rise
to about 9 million in
2030, 10 million in 2040.
Approximately one in
four persons will develop
heart failure in their
lifetime. The proportion of
younger patients with
heart failure is increasing
compared to the proportion
of older patients.
The incidence and
prevalence of heart
failure is higher
among black individuals
compared with other
racial and ethnic groups.
Highest heart failure death
rates have been reported
in the Midwest, Southeast,
and Southern states.
Rural areas have
significantly higher heart
failure mortality
rates than urban areas.
The next several slides
focus on definitions and
classification of heart
failure. The cardiology
community acknowledges
that the terminology is
confusing, and I will do
my best to clarify it here.
Heart failure can be
classified by the structure
in which case we refer
to cardiomyopathy.
Cardiomyopathy is a term
that describes features of
structural and functional
heart muscle dysfunction.
Cardiomyopathy is not the
focus of this lecture and
I include this summary table
to integrate structural
classification and clinical
classification of heart
failure. I suggest that
you come back to it on your
own as a review after
studying pathology lecture.
Heart failure can be
classified by the ventricle
involved, left versus right,
although this is in part an
artificial division
because the ventricles are
functional and structurally
related to each other. Left
-sided dysfunction can
contribute to the right-sided
dysfunction, and vice versa,
and the two often coexist.
The functional
classification is probably
the one most commonly
used clinically.
Older terminology
here is systolic
and diastolic heart failure.
New terminology is
heart failure with
reduced ejection
fraction and heart
failure with preserved
ejection fraction.
And you see further how
it is categorized based
on the ejection fraction
and the symptoms.
Normal EF is 55 to 70
percent. Most important
to remember here that
the heart failure with
reduced ejection fraction
is defined by the EF less
than 40 percent, and heart
failure with preserved
ejection fraction is
EF 50 percent or more.
The American College
of Cardiology, American
Heart Association stages
of heart failure emphasize
the development and
progression of disease
starting with stage A,
patients at risk for heart
failure but without
current or past symptoms.
The New York Heart
Association classification is
widely used in clinical trials
and cited in literature.
The ACC AHA stages
of heart failure
are shown here in more detail.
What causes heart failure?
This table is from Harrison's
textbook of internal
medicine and is included
for reference only to
illustrate both the
classification and etiology.
Most common etiologies of heart
failure in the U.S.
are hypertension,
MI, diabetes, obesity,
amyloidosis, sarcoidosis,
and infections.
And with the COVID-19
pandemic, investigators have
gained better insights
into the infection and
inflammation-related myocardial
injury and myocarditis.
This is a simplified
explanation of
the heart failure
pathophysiology.
Acute heart failure in
the setting of primarily
systolic dysfunction may
result from an abrupt
insult such as myocardial
infarction or myocarditis,
or more commonly a
worsening of a chronic and
progressive process. After
the inciting event, a
variety of compensatory
mechanisms are activated.
In the short term,
these mechanisms are able
to restore cardiovascular
function to a normal
range, with the
result that the patient
remains asymptomatic.
However, sustained activation
of these mechanisms
lead to secondary end
-organ damage within the
ventricle, with worsening
left ventricular
remodeling and subsequent
cardiac decompensation.
Here is a closer look into
compensatory mechanisms
that may allow the patients
to remain asymptomatic
for months to years
after the initial event.
Neurohormonal activation
starts with the sympathetic
stimulation of the
kidney that leads to the
activation of the venin
angiotensin aldosterone system,
which promotes salt and
water retention, leads
to vasoconstriction of the
peripheral vasculature,
myocyte hypertrophy,
myocyte cell
death, and myocardial fibrosis.
These mechanisms, once
again, facilitate short-term
adaptation by maintaining
blood pressure and profusion
to vital organs. The same
neurohormonal mechanisms
are believed to contribute
to end-organ changes in
the heart and the circulation,
and to the excessive
salt and water retention
in advanced heart failure.
The mechanisms underlying
heart failure with
preserved ejection
fraction are less clear.
The original descriptions
of half-PEF, which is
sometimes how we call
it, focused on diastolic
dysfunction as the primary
mediator of heart failure
signs and symptoms. For
example, classic example would
be older woman with
hypertension. Many other
processes have been implicated
in disease progression,
including vascular
stiffness, renal dysfunction,
metabolic inflammation
related to adiposity,
oxidative stress, and impaired
nitric oxide signaling.
Bringing it all together,
cardiac dysfunction may
manifest as systolic
dysfunction with
impaired contractility,
diastolic dysfunction
with impaired relaxation,
or decreased
ventricular compliance,
or more often than not, both.
The adaptive
mechanisms we mentioned
in the two prior
slides I included on
the bottom half of
this slide as well.
How will patients with
heart failure present, most
commonly with fatigue
and shortness of breath.
It is important to assess
for decreased exercise
tolerance. Maybe they used
to be able to walk one
block or one flight of
stairs and now get tired
with walking less than half
a block or have to rest
several times before
they reach their bedroom
upstairs or can no longer
take New York City subway.
When I evaluate a patient
at risk for heart failure,
I ask about nocturnal
cough and dyspnea in the
recumbent position,
assessing them for orthopnea.
Rarely patients wake
up in the middle
of the night with
difficulty breathing.
That is called paroxysmal
nocturnal dyspnea.
Patients will often
describe using more
pillows than they
used to sleep on,
or even worse,
sleeping in the chair.
Confusion, disorientation,
mood disturbances may
be observed in patients
with severe heart failure,
particularly elderly
patients with cerebral
atherosclerosis and
reduced cerebral perfusion.
To help us understand
presentation of heart
failure, let's
discuss left and right
heart failure in a
little bit more detail.
The effects of left
-sided heart failure are a
consequence of passive
congestion, blood backing
up in the pulmonary
circulation, circulation,
stasis of blood in the
left-sided chambers,
and inadequate
profusion of downstream
tissues leading to
organ dysfunction.
Notice in the classic
Netter's drawing, the man
is sitting up because of
dyspnea and orthopnea,
appears to be utilizing
accessory muscles of
respiration, and has
pulmonary edema on the chest x
-ray, which we will discuss
again in a few minutes.
moving on to the right
heart failure as a result of
the inability of the left
ventricle to pump the blood
forward appropriately pulmonary
pressures are increased
and that overloads the
right ventricle elevated
pressure and congestion in the
systemic veins will manifest
in jaguar vein engorgement
and hepatic congestion.
This patient is depicted to be
cyanotic with peripheral edema,
JVD, and hepatomegaly.
Cardiac and pulmonary
causes of right heart
failure are listed
here. The most common
cause of right-sided
heart failure is actually
the presence of left
-sided heart failure.
Isolated right heart
failure is less common
and usually reflects
increased right
ventricular afterload
due to diseases of the
lung parenchyma or
pulmonary vasculature.
Right-sided heart disease
that results from a
primary pulmonary
process is known as core
pulmonale, mentioned in one
of the first slides, which
may lead to symptoms
of right heart failure.
What physical exam
findings will be
helpful in the diagnosis
of heart failure?
In the advanced
heart failure, blood
pressure may be
reduced because of
severe left ventricular
dysfunction.
General appearance.
Patients may have labored
breathing. They may not be
able to finish a sentence
because of shortness
of breath. They may
have cool extremities and
cyanosis of the lips and
nail beds due to peripheral
vasoconstriction.
Pulmonary crackles result
from the transudation
of fluid from the
intravascular space into the
alveoli if cardiomegal
is present the PMI point
of maximal impulse
usually is displaced below
the fifth intercostal
space or lateral to the
midclavicular line and
the impulse is palpable
over two interspaces an
S3 or S4 may be present
Peripheral edema is a
cardinal manifestation
of heart failure,
but it is nonspecific
and may be absent
in patients who have
been treated adequately
with diuretics.
Peripheral edema is usually
symmetric and dependent
in heart failure and occurs
predominantly in the ankles
and the pre-tibial region
in ambulatory patients.
In bedridden patients, edema
may be found in the sacral
area, that's pre-sacral
edema, and the *******.
Keep that in mind next
year when you're examining
hospitalized patients or even
wheelchair-bound patients.
And then long-standing
edema may be also
associated with indurated
and pigmented skin.
Specific cardiovascular
physical exam techniques
are well explained in
the Bates textbook and
will be reviewed again
in your DPR sessions.
To evaluate for JVD, which
provides an estimation
of the right atrial
pressure, I will lift the
head of the exam table
to 45 degrees and gently
turn the patient's head
to the opposite side.
Pressure on the liver
will make it more obvious
as a result of hepatojugular
reflex. It may take
a few seconds, though that
wouldn't be immediate.
In addition to physical
exam, a chest x-ray provides
useful information about
cardiac size and shape,
as well as the state of
the pulmonary vasculature.
A routine 12 lead EKG
is recommended to assess
cardiac rhythm and determine
the presence of left
ventricular hypertrophy
or prior MI, as well as to
determine QRS with, and
we'll touch upon that again.
These patients should
have a complete
blood count, electrolytes,
hepatic enzymes,
thyroid function
test, lipid panel,
as well as cardiac
enzymes checked.
The most useful test
is the echocardiogram,
which can provide an assessment
of left ventricular
size and function,
valvular or wall
motion abnormalities,
indicative of a prior MI.
Here is the algorithm for
the diagnosis of heart
failure and EF-based
classification to summarize or
visually represent the
information we discussed.
Natriuretic peptides,
specifically the BNP and
N-terminal ProBNP, play
a role in diagnosis and
prognostication. Higher
concentrations inform
high risk risk in patients
with dyspnea, if there
is a clinical uncertainty
about the diagnosis,
for example, pulmonary
disease versus heart
failure as the cause
of the symptoms, then
measurement of BNP and
proBNP is useful to
support making diagnosis
of heart failure.
We now are shying
away from using
these biomarkers
and prognostication.
Not only are they expensive,
they can also not
be so helpful.
For example, we need
to recognize limitation
of these biomarkers
as listed here.
To help illustrate possible
EKG changes in heart
failure, I'm including
this EKG and an associated
clinical case from
the website EKG Maven.
84-year-old woman
with heart failure.
The main abnormality here
is the rhythm. It is not
sinus. If you look at the
lead 2 on the bottom as your
rhythm strip, you do not
see a P wave preceding QRS.
What other changes can be seen
on the EKG in heart failure?
Ventricular
hypertrophy, as well as
arrhythmias, conduction
abnormalities,
past MI, or evidence
of active ischemia.
This particular EKG
shows clear evidence
of left ventricular
hypertrophy with T-wave
inversions in the
lateral leads here and
very prominent voltage
in the chest leads.
There are many
criteria for LVH which
are beyond the scope
of this lecture.
Another important
part of the diagnosis
of heart failure
is chest x-ray.
Typical findings in acute heart
failure are bilateral, diffuse,
alveolar infiltrates,
coalescing with
each other in the
butterfly pattern.
You will also see it
described as a bat wing
pattern, and that is
typical of pulmonary edema.
We may also see bilateral
pleural effusion with
blunted costophenic angles.
This is not seen here.
This is a sharp
claustrophene angle, and this
is a little bit fuzzy,
but overall we don't see
bilateral pleural effusion
here. We see minor
pleural effusion in the
right horizontal fissure.
Curly lines are the
results of interstitial
edema and increased
lymphatic drainage. Here
is a classic approach
to acute decompensated
heart failure based on
four hemodynamic profiles.
This classification
helps guide initial
therapy and prognosis
for patients
presenting with
advanced heart failure.
The history and physical
exam allows estimation
of the patient's
hemodynamic status, that
is the degree of
congestion, dry versus wet,
as well as adequacy of
the peripheral perfusion,
warm versus cold. How can
we tell if the patient
is congested? Patient can
complain of orthopnea.
We may notice elevated JVP
or an S3 sound crackles
on your lung exam, as
well as peripheral edema.
cold refers to hyperperfusion
cool extremities low
urine output nausea even
abdominal pain low blood
pressure elevated LFTs
elevated lactate as a result
of hyperperfusion the
most common combination of
peripheral perfusion and
congestion probably more
than 70% of patients with
advanced decompensated
heart failure is the warm
and wet clinical profile.
This group of patients
typically present with either
normal or markedly
elevated systolic blood
pressure. A minority of
patients will present with the
cold and wet clinical
profile. This would include
patients with cardiogenic
shock, low output
syndrome. Patients in this
category, I'd increase risk
of death and cardiac
transplantation at one year.
Compared with patients
with heart failure
would reduce TF with a
warm and wet profile.
And then less than 10%
of patients with advanced
decompensated heart
failure will present
with warm and dry or
cold and dry profiles.
Moving on to the management
of heart failure. In
2022, American Heart
Association published new
guidelines for the
management of heart failure.
The next several slides
we will discuss the
main principles of the
pharmacologic management.
In addition, lifestyle
modifications have been
the topic of many clinical
trials and debates.
Sodium restriction to
two to three grams a day
seems reasonable and
beneficial for most patients.
Unfortunately, the
typical American diet
contains much higher
amount of sodium than that.
Fluid restriction is
not recommended for most
patients, except those
in stage D, and even for
them, up to two liters
a day should be okay.
Alcohol and smoking
cessation is definitely
beneficial for patients.
A cardiac rehab program
can be useful to improve
functional capacity,
exercise tolerance,
and quality of life.
Use of cardiac devices
for selected patients
is beneficial as
well, and we will
discuss that in a
little bit more detail.
Palliative care is particularly
important in patients
with advanced heart failure
to support discussion
of treatment goals, shared
decision-making regarding
mechanical circulatory
support, and transplantation.
In patients with heart
failure symptoms and
reduced EF, the goals of
therapy are to reduce symptom
severity, prevent
hospitalization for worsening
heart failure, and
decrease the risk of
mortality and morbidity,
possibly reverse the process
of adverse remodeling
of the left ventricle.
Guideline-directed
medical therapy now
includes four pillars,
as you see here,
or quadruple therapy
that includes
angiotensin receptor
nephrolysin inhibitor,
beta blocker,
mineralocorticoid receptor
antagonist, and
SGLT2 inhibitor.
No standard medical
treatment regimen exists for
heart failure with preserved
ejection fraction. and
treatment is typically
focused on use of diuretics to
relieve congestion and
management of comorbidities
and presence of underlying
cardiovascular disease.
There is new evidence,
however, that SGLT2 inhibitors
can be beneficial in
decreasing heart failure
hospitalizations and cardiovascular
mortality in this group.
Aldosterone antagonists
may be considered
to decrease hospitalizations
as well as RNA.
Recent evidence suggests
that GLP-1 agonists are
beneficial for heart
failure with preserved
ejection fraction patients
if they also have obesity.
This has not been
proven in patients with
heart failure with reduced
ejection fraction yet.
Here is the algorithm
from the American
Heart Association
that illustrates
the information on
the previous slide.
The guidelines for
treatment of patients with
mildly reduced EF,
that's one of those
intermediate classification,
if you remember previous
slide, for classification
based on the EF,
are similar.
The numbers in the boxes
here correspond to the level
of evidence, and there
is more information about
it in the article that I'm
referencing. This is not
meant for memorizing,
rather for reference and
general understanding. For
example, there is higher
level of evidence from
the clinical trials about
usefulness of diuretics in
this patient, therefore level
one evidence. Weaker
recommendations are made for
ARNI, ACE inhibitor, ARB,
mineralocorticoid receptor
antagonist and better
blockers in this population.
This is an advanced
pharmacotherapeutic slide that
is included for completeness
and your future reference
rather than memorization
or testing purposes.
It will become more
apparent in clinical years
to come. I will just
give you one example. In
patients with congestion,
if perfusion is adequate,
remember your wet and warm
patient, the treatment
option will include
vasodilator and diuretic.
Let's talk about salt and heart
failure, or sodium
to be precise.
Generations of physicians
have been taught
that high-sodium diet
is harmful for patients.
It turns out that we
don't have the evidence
from clinical trials
to back that assertion.
We know that a typical
American diet has upwards of
3 to 4 grams of sodium a
day, While when patients are
admitted to the hospital
due to heart failure or any
other cardiac issue, we
place them on a low-sodium
diet, which they absolutely
hate, find food tasting
really bad, and then do not
follow when they go home.
Here are the results of
a large international
randomized controlled
trial in chronic
heart failure that did
not show significant
benefit in patients
on low-sodium diet.
This is a topic that needs
further research, and most
physicians agree on
restricting patients with
advanced heart failure to 2
to 3 grams of sodium a day.
Patients with chronic
heart failure should be
instructed to monitor
their daily weights, to
know their target weight.
This may be important
due to volume overload,
and we teach patients
to weigh themselves
daily, keep a logbook.
Multiple members of the
healthcare team that
interact with patients
between physicians visit
play an important role
here. These measures seem
logical and relatively
low cost. However, they
have not been shown to
prevent hospitalizations.
Exercise training and
cardiac rehab have been shown
by the evidence from
randomized clinical trials to
improve functional status,
exercise performance, and quality
of life in patients with
heart failure with reduced
ejection fraction and
preserved ejection fraction.
Arrhythmias are a
common cause of death in
patients with heart
failure, and an ICD improves
survival when used
for both primary and
secondary prevention of
sudden cardiac death.
mechanical circulatory support
with a left ventricular
assist device, LVAD, is
a life-saving therapy for
patients with decompensating
advanced heart failure
who fail to improve with
optimal medical therapy.
It is a rapidly evolving
field, and there may be more
advanced devices currently
being used than the one
pictured here. And there
are more of these patients
living in the community
now while previously they
were confined to the hospital
icus which was the case
during my residency training
this is extraordinary
expensive treatment however
it can be life-saving
and it is used for patients
while waiting for heart
transplants or those
that do not qualify for a
transplant patients with
advanced heart failure
should be referred to
multidisciplinary disease
management programs with
the goal of improving
communication between hospital
and outpatient settings.
The transition from
inpatient to outpatient
care can be an especially
vulnerable period because
of the complex medical
regimens, as you'll
see in the following
slide, the large number
of comorbid conditions,
and multiple clinicians
specialists specialists
who may be involved.
Patients are at highest
risk for decompensation
requiring readmission
in the days and weeks
immediately following
post-hospital discharge.
It is recommended that
primary care physicians follow
up with these patients
within seven days after they
discharge from the hospital
to go over discharge
instructions, explain diet
restrictions, ensure that
patients have access to new
medications, and understand
changes that were made in
their medication regimen.
Seven-day recommendation
is something we in
our Central Islip Family
Health Center find
challenging, but it is
definitely the goal.
This is a common
representation of a list of
medications that a primary
care physician is faced
with at the hospital
follow-up visit. In our
health center, I work
with a nurse and our third
and fourth year students
to reconcile discharge
medications for the patient.
It can take all of us
quite some time to review
the list, so you can
imagine that there is a
lot of room for errors.
This would be a better way
for pharmacy to package
medications as opposed
to patient keeping each
medication in a separate
container, reading dosing
instructions and following
them several times a day.
You also see here an example
from the American Heart
Association of the medicine
chart where dosing and
prescribing information
can be clearly documented.
There are significant
racial, age and gender
disparities and heart
failure that affect
outcomes. Some examples are
listed here. These These
disparities warrant
further studies and health
policy changes to
address health inequity.
Coming back to our case.
This patient presents
with dyspnea, JVD,
NS3 heart sound and peripheral
edema, suggesting
heart failure.
X-ray of the chest
revealed enlarged cardiac
silhouette and EKG shows
evidence of prior MI.
You see the Q waves.
You were given that
in the stem. These
findings suggest heart
failure is the cause
of his symptoms, and
most likely heart
failure would reduce TF.
Most likely cause of heart
failure would reduce TF
is coronary artery disease,
and this is supported
by the history of MI,
diabetes, and EKG findings.
Looking at other answer
choices, alcohol in excess
can cause dilated
cardiomyopathy,
and that would be less common.
Viral myocarditis
as a result of the two
viruses given here as answer
choices, that would be
less frequent and more
importantly, less likely
in this clinical scenario.
Aortic stenosis, there is no
evidence in the physical exam.
Sarcomia gene
mutation, that would be
more in the younger
population and less
frequent than coronary
artery disease.
In summary, heart failure
is a complex clinical
syndrome with symptoms and
signs that result from any
structural functional
impairment of either
ventricular filling or ejection
of blood. Two major types
of heart failure are
heart failure with reduced
ejection fraction and
preserved ejection fraction.
Classic symptoms of acute heart
failure are exertional dyspnea,
paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea,
orthopnea, and
peripheral edema.
And of course, the
guideline directed medical
therapy for heart failure
with reduced ejection
fraction is now four
medication classes
listed here and diuretics
for volume overload.
This is also a nice summary
from one of your textbooks.
Please let me know
any questions that
you have and thank
you very much.